FILIPPO CASTELLANI

PhD Candidate in Biorobotics

Birth date: 5th Feb 1999

Portfolio Website

castellanifilippo5@gmail.com

+39 3482740303

github.com/FilippoCastellani

Paris, France

in /in/filippo-castellani

SUMMARY

Biomedical Engineering student driven by a profound interest in Neuroscience, Brain-Computer Interfaces (BCI), and AI-driven solutions for rehabilitation.

I have a solid engineering background, reinforced by hands-on experience acquired in clinical settings and conducting experiments with technical instruments and biological tissues. With my work, I aim to make significant contributions to the field of biomedical solutions, enhancing the well-being of patients affected by neural disabilities.

TECHNICAL EXPERTISE -

Coding Python, Matlab, C++,

Languages: JavaScript, SQL, HTML, CSS.

Electro- EEG acquisition, **Physiology:** EMG acquisition,

FES stimulation,

Neural population recording using

Multi-Electrode Arrays.

EXPERIENCE

10/2023 - 04/2024 Research internship (Master Thesis)

Institut de La Vision (Sorbonne Université), Paris, FR

- Research visual information encoding in biological neural networks, in particular, in the retina.
- · Study Retinal Ganglion Cells response through Multi-Electrode Array recording on ex-vivo mouse retina.
- Devise and carry out experiments to probe and explore visual information encoding mechanisms during biomimetic stimulation.
- Analyse the electrophysiological response of neurons to uncover the mechanisms behind poorly understood color encoding.

11/2021 - 09/2023 Neurotechnology Researcher

RECOMMENCER Project: Currently undergoing clinical trial - NCT05511207

S.Lucia Foundation IRCCS, Rome, IT

- Implementation of a bidirectional Brain Computer Interface (BCI) for upper limb rehabilitation in poststroke subjects.
- Develop real-time algorithm to perform electroencephalographic (EEG), electromyographic (EMG) signals analysis and eventually extracting Corticomuscular Coherence features.
- Code and test the features classification logic that relays neurofeedback through Functional Electrical Stimulation (FES).
- Design and integrate information processing modules in a cohesive data pipeline, from acquisition to sensorial neurofeedback.
- Create the therapist interface for rehabilitation session management. Write documentation and software version management.

PUBLICATIONS

2022

Cortico-Muscular Coupling to Control a Hybrid Brain-Computer Interface for Upper Limb Motor Rehabilitation: A Pseudo-Online Study on Stroke Patients.

de Seta, V.; Toppi, J.; Colamarino, E.; Molle, R.; Castellani, F.; Cincotti, F.; Mattia, D.; Pichiorri, F.

PROJECTS

Up-to-Date

My projects

Portfolio

Collection of recent, past and ongoing projects.

EDUCATION

9/2021 - today scholarship holder

MSc Biomedical Engineering - Technologies for Electronics

Politecnico di Milano, Milan, IT

Thesis: currently under development

9/2018 - 10/2021 scholarship holder

BSc Clinical Engineering

Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome, IT

Thesis: Coherence-Based BCI for Rehabilitation: Feature Extraction and Experimental Assessment

- Perform research on state of-the-art use of coherence-based BCI.
- Implementing via Python, a feature extraction algorithm executable within the OpenVibe Software framework.
- · Conduct laboratory test of features extraction from non-pathological subjects.

9/2011 - 9/2019

Jazz Drum [2011-2015] and Electronic Music [2018-2019]

Conservatory of Music Santa Cecilia, Rome, IT

- · Completed coursework in composition, music theory, application of signal theory to sound design.
- · Proficient in solfége, pianoforte, Jazz drumming techniques, as well as orchestral performance.

LANGUAGES